A Guide to the Papers of the Ambler and Barbour Families, 1772-1880
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the Ambler and Barbour Families, 1772-1880
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
38-77
This collection contains 2,000 items (9 ft.).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Scope and Content Information
The components of the collection are the personal and business papers of John Jaquelin Ambler (1801-1854) of Glenambler, Amherst County, Virginia, a landowner and farmer, of his father in law Philip Pendleton Barbour (1783-1841) of Orange County, Virginia, a lawyer, politician, and jurist: approximately half of the collection derives from each man.
Ambler's papers include containing a brief autobiography to 1823, the journal of his travels in Europe during 1823-1826, an autobiography for the years 1826-1836; estate accounts for Glenambler and a second property called St. Moor; and business or personal correspondence of Ambler, his wife Elizabeth Barbour Ambler, parents John Ambler (1762-1836) and Catherine Bush Abler (1773-1846), half brother Daniel Norborn Norton (1794-1842), brothers Philip St. George (1806-1877) and Richard Cary Ambler (1810-1877), sister-in-law and mother-in-law Philippa and Mrs. Philip Pendleton Barbour, and various other members of the Ambler and Barbout families. The estate and business papers, related to Lynchburg, Campbell and Amhurst counties, Virginia, concern sales of crops, charges for labor and supplies, and Ambler's keen interest in fine horses and acquisition of lands. The personal correspondence originates in Amherst County, Richmond, and Orange County in Virginia, and in Washington, D.C.
Barbour's papers include four accounts books recording charges and payments for legal services ca. 1806-1828 rendered during his practice in Charlottesville, and in Albemarle, Louisa, Madison, Orange, and King and Queen counties, in Virginia, as well as legal correspondence and receipts and other papers arising from the law practice and the business of Barbour's plantation, 1801-1829. The collection offers very little material on Barbour's political and judicial career.
Contents List
- Journal of John Jaquelin Ambler of "Glen Ambler," 1801-1854., 4 vols., each with his armorial bookplate.
  - Volume 1. (Box 1)
    The first volume opens with "Memoranda of the life of John Jaqueline Ambler of Glen Ambler" (pp.1-19), a brief autobiography of the writer up to August 1823 when he embarked on the East Indiaman Palambam, Capt. George Simpson, for London. Ambler's journal follows (pp. 1-329), with an account of his travels August 1823- September 1824 in England, France, Belgium, Holland, Germany, Switzerland and Italy.
  - Volume 2., 311 pages (Box 2)
    Covers Ambler's travels September 1824- August 1825 in Italy, France, and England.
  - Volume 3., 318 pages (Box 2)
    Records his residence in England August- December 1825.
  - Volume 4., 311 pages (Box 2)
    Covers residence December 1825- April 1826 in England and France, whence Ambler sailed for home; pp. 224-225 have trivial appendixes of 1827 and 1828; pp. 226-311 continues Ambler's "Memoranda," in autobiography for the period 1826-1836.
- Letters of Philip Pendleton Barbour to John Jaquelin Ambler, his wife Elizabeth Barbour Ambler, and his mother-in-law, Mrs. Frances T. Barbour, 1832-1847., 12 items. (Box 3)
  Philip Pendleton Barbour (1783-1841), a lawyer of Orange County, was member of the General Assembly 1812-1814; House Representative from Va., 1814-1821; speaker, 1821-1823; judge of Virginia judiciary 1825; Congress 1827-1830; president VA Court Convention, 1829-1830; chairman of judiciary committee; president Philadelphia free trade convention, 1831. Was appointed associate justice of U.S. Supreme Court in 1836. Judge US District Court 1830.
  Most of the letters are from Ambler brothers and Mrs. Barbour's children.
- Legal Papers of Philip Pendleton Barbour, 1802-1812., 12 items. (Box 3)
- Letters to Philip Pendleton Barbour., 120 items. (Box 3)
- Copies of wills and other legal documents, ca. 1780-1811., 132 items. (Box 3)
  Much of the documents are of Orange and Albemarle counties.
- Albemarle, Louisa, Madison, Orange Cos. Bills accounts, receipts, notes, Philip Pendleton Barbour et al., 1801-1810., 786 items. (Box 4)
  These bills, etc. often seem to relate to Philip Pendleton Barbour's correspondence above.
- King and Queen, Louisa, Orange, Charlottesville, Albemarle county Bills, Accounts, Receipts, Notes, etc., 1811-1816., 928 items. (Box 5)
- Legal papers and correspondence, 1812-1823., 174 items. (Box 6)
  Correspondence include letters to Philip Pendleton Barbour, various letters to John Jaquelin Ambler in 1822-23, and a few letters to John Jaquelin Amber's father.
- Bills, receipts, notes, etc., 1817-1821., 786 items. (Box 7)
- Bound volume estate accounts for "Glen Ambler" and Saint Moor, ca. 1822-1830. (Box 8)
  Includes newspaper clippings on estates, races, pedigrees. Book label of John Jaquelin Ambler, Richmond, Virginia.
- Letters to John Jaquelin Ambler, etc., 1823-1826., 225 items. (Box 9)
  Some of the letters are to John Ambler, Daniel N. Norton, et al. Also included are estate papers from 1823-1824.
- Letters to John Jaquelin Ambler, etc., 1824-1826., 151 items. (Box 10)
  Some letters are sent to John Ambler, Daniel N. Norton, Philip Pendleton Barbour, especially in 1826, et al. Included are estate papers from 1825 of particular interested, as well as letters from Philip St. George Ambler at the University of Virginia.
- John Jaquelin Ambler business memos and Letters to Philip Pendleton Barbour, John Jaquelin Ambler, et al., 1826-1829., Memos are bound. 131 items. (Box 11)
  Included are letters from Richard Cary Ambler at the University of Virginia, 1827-1828.
- Philip Pendleton Barbour bills, etc, 1824-1826., ca. 200 items. (Box 12)
- The Franklin Almanac for ...1826 (Richmond, Virginia). (Box 12)
  Includes manuscript inserts of notes on weather, planting, cattle, occasional notes on pages of the almanac, deaths, sale of slaves.
- Philip Pendleton Barbour, John Jacquelin Ambler et al., bills, etc., 1827., 229 items. (Box 12)
- Philip Pendleton Barbour, John Jacquelin Ambler, bills, etc., 1828., 182 items. (Box 12)
- Philip Pendleton Barbour, John Jaquelin Ambler, bills, etc., 1829., 196 items. (Box 12)
- Letters to Mr. And Mrs. John Jacquelin Ambler, 1829, Fragments and undated items, many of them receipts, etc. 450 items. (Box 13)
  Mostly family correspondence, with one letter to Philip Pendleton Barbour, and one from Richard Cary Ambler.
- Letters to Mr. and Mrs. J.J. Ambler, 1829-1830., 144 items. (Box 14)
  Some letters are family, some business; with a few letters to John Ambler and wife to Philip Pendleton Barbour et al.
- Letters to John Jaquelin Ambler and wife, and a fair number to and from Mr. and Mrs. Philip Pendleton Barbour, 1830-1831., 128 items> (Box 15)
  Most of the letters are family, personal.
- Letters to John Jaquelin Ambler and Philip Pendleton Barbour, 1831-1832., 134 items. (Box 16)
  Those letters to Ambler largely concerned his intended ride of a horse.
- Letters to and from John Jaquelin Ambler, etc., 1832-1833., 80 items. (Box 17)
- Letter to John Jaquelin Ambler, 1833., 53 items. (Box 17)
  Mostly concerning horses, estate matters.
- Letter to Philip Pendleton Barbour, miscellaneous, 1833., 14 items. (Box 17)
- Overseer agreements, 1820-1821., 2 items. (Box 17)
- Memorandum St. Moor etc., 1822-1823., 2 items. (Box 17)
- Agreements, etc. 1833., 3 items. (Box 17)
- Estate agreements, 1823-1825., 4 items. (Box 17)
- Philip Pendleton Barbour-John Jaquelin Ambler, 183- Dec. 19., 1 item. (Box 17)
- Article of agreement, etc., 1829-1830., 3 items. (Box 17)
- Article of agreement, etc., 1831., 3 items. (Box 17)
- Correspondence of Philip Pendleton Barbour, 1834., 12 items. (Box 17)
- Correspondence of J.J. Ambler and wife, 1834., 78 items. (Box 17)
- Correspondence of J.J. Ambler, 1835., 64 items. (Box 17)
- Correspondence of Philip Pendleton Barbour, 1835., 3 items. (Box 17)
- John Jaquelin Ambler and Philip Pendleton Barbour, bills and etc., 1836., 1,085 items. (Box 18)
- Miscellaneous material, probably of John Jaquelin Ambler and Philip Pendleton Barbour, 1811-1832. (Box 19)
- Printed material of John Jaquelin Ambler and Philip Pendleton Barbour, 1836-1839. (Box 19)
- Corrspondence of John Jaquelin Ambler and Philip Pendleton Barbour, 1840-1856. (Box 19)
- Miscellaneous material, 1858. (Box 19)
- Bills, etc. of Ambler and Barbour, 1837-1845, 1,034 items. (Box 20)
- Barbour and Ambler bills and miscellaneous, 181?. (Box 21)
- Barbour and Ambler Bills, etc., miscellaneous, 1846-1870. (Box 21)
- Ambler and Barbour checks, 1830-1846. (Box 21)
- Petitions to Judge Barbour from Louisa, Madison, Spotsylvania, 1826. (Box 21)
- Legal Papers and miscellaneous material, probably all of Philip Pendleton Barbour, ca. 1802-1841., ca. 120 items. (Box 21)
- Ledger B., account book of Philip Pendleton Barbour, ca. 1806-1810., 120 pages. (Box 21)
  Contains fees and payments for legal services, notes of family business, births, miscellaneous accounts, with ca. 1811-1834 on end papers and a separate index laid in.
- Ledger C, account book of Philip Pendleton Barbour, ca. 1810-1824., 12 pages. (Box 21)
  Contains fees and payments for legal services.
- Ledger D, account book of Philip Pendleton Barbour, ca. 1813-1828., 198 pages. (Box 21)
  Contains fees and payments for legal services. Further accounts 1839-1840 evidently of estate business in end papers.
- Ledger E, account book of Philip Pendleton Barbour, ca. 1822-1826., 68 pages. (Box 21)
  Contains fees and payments for legal services. Also account of advance payments to Elizabeth Ambler 1828-1831 (f. 70), and Dr. Thomas Barbour, n.d. (ff. 72-73).